Guide to the Committee on Christian Literature For Women and Children in Mission Fields, Inc. Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Committee on Christian Literature For Women and Children in Mission Fields, Inc. Records
1909-1989
RG 90
Yale University Divinity School Library
7.5
(18 boxes)
The archives document the work of an organization run by women for women. They provide insight into developing concepts of the role of Christian literature and related artwork overseas. The Committee was formed in 1912 under the sponsorship of the Federation of Women's Boards of Foreign Missions. Its goal was to provide Christian literature to women and children overseas. In the first fifty years of its existence the Committee supported 27 magazines, 9 of which were originated by the Committee. Beginning in the 1940s, the Committee began to make grants for literacy projects as well. The Committee had an increasingly cooperative relationship with the Committee on World Literacy and Christian Literature (formed in 1942 by the Foreign Missions Conference of North America) and with its successor, the Intermedia Committee of the National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A. In 1989 the Committee on Christian Literature for Women and Children ceased to exist as a separate entity and became a Standing Committee within Intermedia.
Committee on Christian Literature For Women and Children in Mission Fields, Inc.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Committee on Christian Literature for Women and Children in Mission Fields, Inc., 1989. Gift of the Baldwin Library of Historical Children's Literature at the University of Florida, 2013
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Traveling in the Far East in the early years of this century, three women were impressed by the need for Christian outreach to women and children. Upon their return, Miss Clementina Butler, Mrs. Henry W. Peabody and Mrs. Helen Barrett Montgomery worked together toward the formation in 1912 of the Committee on Christian Literature for Women and Children in Missions Fields. The CCLWCMF was formed under the sponsorship of the Federation of Women's Boards of Foreign Missions and members of the Committee were appointed by Mission boards. The initial goal of the CCLWCMF was to print books but it was soon decided that periodicals were a more expedient method of assisting women and children in the mission fields. The Committee's first project, in 1913, was support of The Women's Messenger, a magazine in China. Three other magazines were supported during the first decade of the Committee's existence: Happy Childhood (China), Light of Love (Japan) and Women's Magazine (Latin America).
During the next decades, numerous magazines received CCLWCMF support. In most cases the magazines were published by missionaries or national groups and received primarily financial support from the Committee. The Committee received financial support from the World Day of Prayer, beginning in the early 1920s, as well as from individual donors.
The magazines sponsored by the Committee were not entirely religious in nature. The Treasure Chest, for example, published in India in both English and vernacular dialects, contained articles on science and health, games, puzzles and fiction, as well as Christian teachings. El Taliba was published in Egypt in Arabic and distributed jointly by the Egyptian Y.W.C.A. and the United Presbyterian Mission. It was not labeled as a Christian publication, so as to be acceptable in Islamic homes. The magazine Listen in Africa was another of the Committee's major projects, financed by CCLWCMF funds and sponsored by the International Committee on Christian Literature for Africa. It contained articles on health, school subjects, art, world history as well as religious stories, and placed special emphasis on encouraging Africans in art and in writing. From its early days, the CCLWCMF sought to support indigenous Christian artists and spared no expense in securing colorful covers for the magazines it sponsored. In later years, it also sponsored the publication of picture books for children and illustrated booklets.
In the first fifty years of its existence the CCLWCMF supported twenty-seven magazines; nine of these were started by the Committee. Beginning in the 1940s, the Committee began to make grants for literacy projects in addition to the continued support of periodical publications. The CCLWCMF had an increasingly cooperative relationship with the Committee on World Literacy and Christian Literature ("Lit-Lit"), formed in 1942 by the Foreign Missions Conference of North America. In 1955 a survey of the world program of Christian literature was jointly proposed by the CCLWCMF and "Lit-Lit". This survey and a full-time executive director of the CCLWCMF were made possible by a generous bequest from Marguerite Doane in 1956.
A formal "Basis of Cooperation" was signed between the CCLWCMF and "Lit-Lit" in 1958, and again between the CCLWCMF and the Intermedia Committee, into which "Lit-Lit" had merged in 1970. During the two decades after the appointment of full time Executive Director Marion Van Horne, workshop programs to train writers were emphasized and cooperation with other groups and agencies stressed. The Children's Book Fund, launched in 1964, and the "80 Miles of Children's Books" project brought about the production of hundreds indigenous children's books. In 1970 a new program of developmental literature for women was begun to undergird programs of public health, nutrition, community development, vocational training and economic justice. Scholarships were granted to indigenous writers and artists to enable them to obtain further training.
Marion Van Horne retired from full-time service in 1981 and David Bridwell of Intermedia served as Acting Director of the CCLWCMF on a part-time basis. In 1989 the CCLWCMF ceased to exist as a separate entity and became a Standing Committee for Women and Children within the Intermedia Committee.
Scope and Contents
These archives document the work of the Committee in a thorough way. An historical awareness on the part of Committee members regarding the originality, integrity and success of this work for women by women is evident in the archives. The available records would support study of the Committee as a type of woman's movement emerging in the early twentieth century, as well as study of its strong-minded woman leaders, such as Clementina Butler, Helen Barrett Montgomery and Marion Van Horne. The archives contain valuable primary data documenting Christian literature initiatives and discussion regarding issues of indigenous language and art pertinent to the Christian literature enterprise.
The Organization and Policy Records of Series I provide systematic chronological documentation of the programs and status of the Committee. The bulk of the Series consists of the contents of "minute books" compiled by the Committee - notebooks including not only minutes of meetings but also pertinent memoranda and related documents.
The Committee did not have a full-time salaried executive director during the early years of its existence, but there was always a "chairman" of the Committee or prominent shaper and mover in the organization. The Executive Files of Series II are the files available for eight of these leaders. No files were available for Mrs. Henry W. Peabody who served as chairman from 1913 to 1919, but early documentation regarding the Committee is available in the files of Clementina Butler. Most extensive are the files of Marion Van Horne, who served as Executive Director from 1957 to 1981.
The Histories and Publications of Series III document the origins, development and program of the CCLWCMF. Narrative histories of the Committee, program booklets, and publicity brochures are included, as well as samples of periodicals sponsored by the Committee and a complete run of The Word at Work, which began as a publication of the World Literacy and Christian Literature Committee.
The core of the Committee's work was its financial support of publications and projects. Central to Series IV, Financial Records and Correspondence, is the so-called "Red Book" compiled by Sue Weddell in 1958. Through it, one can trace the operations of the Committee during its first five decades. The majority of the correspondence in this Series concerns two bequests received by the Committee. A bequest from Helen Barrett Montgomery was received before the Committee was incorporated and had to be placed under the aegis of another organization. This led to various complications.
The Surveys and Studies of Series V provide valuable documentation regarding indigenous Christian literature programs throughout the world during the 1960s and 1970s.
The Photographs of Series VI date primarily from the 1970s.
The Addendum consists of files that were transferred to the Yale Divinity Library from the Baldwin Library of Historical Children's Literature at the University of Florida. These files had been donated to Baldwin Library at some point in the past, without clear provenance. The material in the addendum dates primarly from the tenure of Marion Van Horne, who served as Executive Director from 1957 to 1981, with some minutes from earlier and later years.
Arrangement
I. Organization and Policy Records, 1918-1989
II. Executive Files, 1909-1986
III. Histories and Publications, 1927-1983
IV. Financial Records and Correspondence, 1912-1989
V. Surveys and Studies, 1964-1973
VI. Photographs,1966-1980
VII. Addendum, 1918-1986
Christian literature -- Publishing; Women in church work; Butler, Clementina; Montgomery, Helen Barrett, 1861-1934; Committee on Christian Literature For Women and Children in Mission Fields, Inc.
- Organization and Policy Records, 1918-1989; Series I
  - Legal documents
    - Certificate of Incorporation, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - By-laws, 1945,1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Agreement between CCLWCMF and NCCCUSA and Committee of Reference and Council of the Foreign Missions Conference of N.A., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - By-laws, 1956,1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Basis of Cooperation between CCLWCMF and Committee on World Literacy and Christian Literature, DFM, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Corporate resolutions, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Basis of Cooperation between CCLWCMF and Intermedia, 1970, 1979
    - By-laws (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minute books
    - List of dates of meetings, 1918-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Contents of Minute books, 1918-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8-24)
    - Contents of Minute books, 1967-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25-41)
  - Additional Board of Directors and committee minutes
    - Board of Directors, 1945-1951 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
    - Board of Directors, 1952-1971 (Box 3, Folder 44-47)
    - Joint Committee on Strategy - Committee on World Literacy and Christian Literature and CCLWCMF, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Committee on Direction of the Survey Study of Lit-Lit and CCLWCMF, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - "Sister colleges" Committee, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Membership lists and correspondence
    - Lists, 1956-1981, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51-53)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1982 (Box 3, Folder 54-60)
- Executive Files, 1909-1986; Series II
  - Alice Kyle
    - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Helen Barrett Montgomery
    - Correspondence, 1930-1931,n.d. (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Biographical information (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Clementina Butler
    - Documents relating to the origins of the CCLWCMF, 1909-1912 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Annual reports, 1939-1943, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Correspondence, 1931-1947, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 66-69)
    - Writings, 1943-1950,n.d. (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Biographical information (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Irene Sheppard
    - Correspondence - general, 1945-1953 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Correspondence - with Clementina Butler, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Correspondence - re. Africa; incl. from Margaret Wrong, 1946-1952 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Correspondence - re. China; Christian Literature Society for China, Margaret Brown, 1944-1952 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - Correspondence - re. China; Council on Christian Literature for Overseas Chinese, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Correspondence - re. China; Mabel Ruth Nowlin, Lyrel Teagarden, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Correspondence - re. China; The Christian Farmer / H. Y. Chang, The Christian Youth / Daniel Lee, 1945-1950 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Correspondence - re. China; with misc. Western agencies, 1943-1951 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Correspondence - re. Europe, 1942-19514 (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - Correspondence- re. India, 1946-1952 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - Correspondence - re. Indonesia, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Correspondence- re. various other countries, 1947-1953 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - Biographical information (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Edna Beardsley
    - Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Sue Weddell
    - Documents re. plan of coordination between CCLWCMF and Committee on World Literacy and Christian Literature, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - re. historical report on CCLWCMF; see also Series IV, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Biographical information (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Marion Van Horne
    - Annual reports, 1968-1979 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Correspondence and documents re. policy and operations of CCLWCMF, 1970-1977,n.d. (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Correspondence and documents re. 60th anniversary of CCLWCMF, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Correspondence and documents re. 80 Miles of Children's Books Project, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Argentina - Arco Iris (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Argentina - Guia del Hogar, 1959-1985 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Hong Kong - Happy Childhood, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Correspondence re. grants - India - Treasure Chest, 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Ireland - Failte, 1980-1982 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Ireland - Hi!, 1977-1982 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Korea - Children's Friend,Christian Home, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Mexico - Antorcha Misionera, 1959-1975 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Mexico - CIDAL, 1972-1980 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Correspondence re. grants - Mexico - Maria, 1975-1979 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Correspondence with Lily Quy, re. work in India, 1982-1983 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Correspondence re.Consultation-Writing Production Workshop, Zambia, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Correspondence re. Middle East trips, 1971,1974 (Box 6, Folder 105)
    - Correspondence re. Training Survey, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 106)
    - Articles and books - "A" - "F" (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Articles and books - Give Children Wings: a manual on how to write for children (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Articles and books - "M" - "T" (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Articles and books - Write the Vision: a manual for writers (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Articles and books - "Writing for New Readers" (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Workshops and travel reports, 1957-1970 (Box 6, Folder 112-114)
    - Consultation-writing workshop for the education of women, Zambia, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 115,116)
    - Workshops and travel reports, 1972-1983,n.d. (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Biographical information (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Kiran Daniels
    - Documents re. CCLWCMF, 1985,1986 (Box 7, Folder 119)
- Histories and Publications, 1927-1983; Series III
  - Narrative histories
    - "History of the CCLWCMF" by Helen Calder, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - "More than Paper and Ink" by Sue Weddell, 1952
    - "The Committee in Retrospect and in Perspective" by Ada P. Stearns, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - "Report of Special Assignment" by Sue Weddell, 1960
    - "Report on the magazine program of the CCLWCMF" by Sue Weddell, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - "CCLWCMF - 55th anniversary" by Elizabeth M. Lee, 1967
    - Sixtieth Anniversary script and audio cassettes, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 123)
    - "Walking Through the Years - 1956-1980" by Marion Van Horne (Box 7, Folder 124)
    - "A Brief Review of the Roots of the CCLWCMF", ca.1982
    - Notes, memo, 1951-1983,n.d. (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Publications of or about the CCLWCMF
    - Publicity brochures, 1927-1977, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 126-128)
    - Program booklets - The Word at Work (began as publication of the World Literacy and Christian Literature Committee), 1924,1942 (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Program booklets - Analysis, 1959-1980 (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - Program booklets - Issues, 1959-1984 (Box 8, Folder 130-132)
    - Articles and pamphlets about the work of the CCLWCMF and/or Christian literature, 1943-1972,n.d. (Box 8, Folder 133)
    - Samples of periodicals supported by CCLWCMF (Box 8, Folder 134)
    - Book lists - "Books for Children and Young People", 1969-1980 (Box 8, Folder 135)
- Financial Records and Correspondence, 1912-1958; Series IV; 2 boxes (1 linear foot)
  - "The Red Book" - summary of work of CCLWCMF, 1912-1958 (Box 8, Folder 136)
  - Audit reports, 1954-1979 (Box 9, Folder 137-141)
  - Disposition of the financial resources of CCLWCMF, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - Support from World Day of Prayer/ Church Women United, 1953-1967 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Support from World Day of Prayer/ Church Women United, 1968-1980,n.d. (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - Helen Barrett Montgomery Bequest, 1934-1965 (Box 9, Folder 145-150)
  - Marguerite Doane Bequest - Contents of notebook labeled "Doane legacy" (Box 10, Folder 151)
  - Marguerite Doane Bequest - Additional correspondence and documents, 1954-1976 (Box 10, Folder 152-156)
  - Hester Bovenkerk Memorial Fund, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 157)
- Surveys and Studies, 1964-1973; Series V
  - Magazine questionnaires, 1964-1967 (Box 10, Folder 158-161)
  - Magazine questionnaires, 1968-1972 (Box 11, Folder 162-166)
  - Survey on the training of writers, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 167)
  - Survey on literature for women - Cover letter, summary sheets, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 168)
  - Survey on literature for women - Questionnaires - Africa, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 169)
  - Survey on literature for women - Questionnaires - Asia, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 170)
  - Survey on literature for women - Questionnaires - Latin America, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 171)
  - Survey on literature for women - Questionnaires - Near East, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 172)
  - Survey on literature for women - Questionnaires - South Pacific, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 173)
  - Analysis of The Treasure Chest, 1965 (Box 12, Folder 174)
- Photographs, Series VI
  - CCLWCMF events
    - Publication of Give Children Wings by Marion Van Horne, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 175)
    - Sixtieth Anniversary, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 176)
    - Celebration of completion of "80 Miles of Children's Books" project, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 177)
  - CCLWCMF brochures
    - "Books Make the World Go 'Round", 1977 (Box 12, Folder 178)
    - "One Good Book Leads to Another", 1980 (Box 12, Folder 179)
    - "Ask Any Woman", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 180)
  - Workshops conducted by Marion Van Horne
    - Argentina, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 181)
    - Mexico, Egypt, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 182)
    - Africa, Cyprus, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 183)
- Addendum, 1918-1986; Series VII
  - Organization and Policy Records
    - 1918-1932 Minute Book (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1955-1957 Minute Book (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1958-1973 Minute Book, pt 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1958-1973 Minute Book, pt 2, 1958-73 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1958-1973 Minute Book, pt 3 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1958-1973 Minute Book, pt 4 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1976-1986 Minute Book, pt 1 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 1976-1986 Minute Book, pt 2 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1976-1986 Minute Book, pt 3 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Executive Files: Marion Van Horne
    - Reports
      - Annual Reports, 1975-1980 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books, General, 1969-1980 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books, Latin America, 1966-1969 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – India 1, 1963-1969 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – India 2, 1970-1973, 1983 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Argentina, 1969-1972 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Brazil, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Burma, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Egypt, 1981-1982 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Ethiopia, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Fiji, 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Hong Kong, 1967-1982 (Box 14, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Indonesia, 1971-1975 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Iran, 1968-1971 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Lebanon, 1970-1971, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Nigeria, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – South Africa, 1968-1972 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – Near East, 1966-1968 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence re. Children's Books – South Pacific, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – Argentina, 1967-1970 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – Al Taliba, 1968-1977 (Box 15, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – Fiji, 1973 (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – India, 1969-1974 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – Indonesia, 1971-1972 (Box 15, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – Iran, 1969-1972 (Box 15, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – Thailand, 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence re. grants, children's books – Turkey, 1965-1983 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Workshops
      - Children's Literature Workshop, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - Ayia Napa International Seminar on Children's Books, 1979
        - Planning Correspondence & Financials (Box 15, Folder 16)
        - Participants (Box 15, Folder 17)
        - Correspondence with Participants (Box 15, Folder 18)
        - Programming & Materials (Box 15, Folder 19)
        - Manuscripts (Box 15, Folder 20)
        - Evaluations (Box 15, Folder 21)
        - Reports on the Seminar (Box 15, Folder 22)
        - "Round-robin" Correspondence after the seminar (Box 15, Folder 23)
      - Salvation Army Workshop, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 24)
      - List of Writer's Workshops Given 1958-1966 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Workshops: Argentina 1966 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - Workshops: Brazil 1976 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Workshops: Brazil 1974 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Workshops: Brazil 1972 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      - Workshops: Cuba 1960 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Workshops: Egypt 1977 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Workshops: Egypt 1975 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - Workshops: Egypt 1965 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Workshops: Fiji 1972 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Workshops: Haiti 1960 (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - Workshops: Hong Kong 1969 (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Workshops: India 1960 (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Workshops: India 1970 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Workshops: India 1963 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - Workshops: India 1968 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Workshops: Indonesia 1977 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Workshops: Indonesia 1971 (Box 17, Folder 6)